<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true coppie of the admonitions sent by the subdued provinces to the states of Hollande and the Hollanders answere to the same. Together vvith the articles of peace concluded betweene the high and mightie princes, Phillip by the grace of God King of Spaine, &amp;c. and Henry the Fourth by the same grace, the most Christian King of France, in the yeare 1598. First translated out of French into Dutch, and nowe into English by H.VV.</title>
            <author>Netherlands.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107297</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842999</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true coppie of the admonitions sent by the subdued provinces to the states of Hollande and the Hollanders answere to the same. Together vvith the articles of peace concluded betweene the high and mightie princes, Phillip by the grace of God King of Spaine, &amp;c. and Henry the Fourth by the same grace, the most Christian King of France, in the yeare 1598. First translated out of French into Dutch, and nowe into English by H.VV.</title>
                  <author>Netherlands.</author>
                  <author>H. W., fl. 1598.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal. aut</author>
                  <author>Spain. Treaties, etc. France, 1598 May 2. English.</author>
                  <author>France. Treaties, etc. Spain, 1598 May 2. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue according to the copie printed in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Belgium --  History --  1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> TRVE COPPIE OF THE ADMONITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS <hi>SENT BY THE SVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued</hi> Provinces to the States of Hollande: and the Hollanders anſwere to the ſame.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER VVITH THE ARTICLES of Peace concluded betweene the high and mightie Princes, PHILLIP <hi>by the grace of God King of</hi> Spaine, <hi>&amp;c. and</hi> HENRY the Fourth by the ſame grace, the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France, in the yeare 1598.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Tranſlated out of French into Dutch, and nowe into Engliſh by H. VV.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBVRGH Printed by Robert Walde-graue according to</hi> the Copie Printed in LONDON. 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="admonitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:2"/>
            <head>To Holland.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
                  </hi> Noble and high minded <hi>Holland,</hi> which act ſo exalted and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe Fortune ſmiles on thee: how long wilt thou liue in this thy wanton fooliſhnes, &amp; begine yourſelfe to force &amp; ſtrength? haſt thou not yet ynough followed the trace of diſquietnes? haſt thou quite forgot the bonde of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitie? is it vpon nothing but blood, murther, and fire that thou ſtudieſt? hath <hi>Mars</hi> wholly poſſeſſed thy hearte? wilt thou haue all according to thy owne minde? Doeſt thou thinke that this will all, way run before the wind with thée? Do but thinke from whome thou art ſeuered? &amp; wherfore hateſt thou them that loued thée? Thou art our fleſh, our blood (in times paſſed in a good mind) but now cruelly bent againſt vs. I cannot imagine wherevpon thy foundation is grounded: twenty fiue yeares thus in ſtrife to continue, will there bee no ende? doth peace goe againſt thy ſtomacke? Doſt thou not ſéeke reſt and tranquility in thy time? Let the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſery mooue thée.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>No Chriſtian is he who in harme taketh delight.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="2">2 Wilt thou perpetually crie and braule, and like ſauage beaſts remaine wild and furious? be theſe thy reformed manners to ſtirre vp mutinies and rebellion? what wilt thou? what ſeekeſt thou? what is thy griefe? wherefore haſt thou taken armes? for thy priuiledges this was the firſt play: but true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that was not it: you ſought ſomething els, as now we may plainely ſee: for the experiences lighteneth thy darknes: thou haſt reiected all dutie: &amp; ſeekeſt (againſt God) a liberty to thy own minde. Open thy eyes, marke if the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach ſuch rules to ſubiectes: What hath S. <hi>Paule</hi> laid before the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians vnder the idolatrous potentates, that they ought to be obedient vnto their ſuperiors according to Gods lawes. This leſſon had alſo bene good in thy behalfe.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>For where pride is, Gods ſpirit cannot abide.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="3">3 It ſeemed that you would baniſh tyranny, and with free hearts defend your patrimony: but you ſought to ſet aſide and ſuppreſſe your ſuperiors, and to liue according to your owne fancy. The ſhewe was faire, but it had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning then ſome thought: but by your workes is apparantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued that yet at this day your heart is againſt ſubiection, you thinke to ſtrengthen your ſelues with your owne force, and deſpiſe the Prince whome God and nature hath giuen thee: He calleth, he watcheth, but thou wilt not heare him: He entreates, he admoniſheth you, and you do not reſpect it: Hee will ioyne himſelfe to you, and you refuſe it: his goodnes augmenteth your rebellion: he deſireth no reuenge, nor cruelty: he will receaue you with grace:
<pb facs="tcp:7702:3"/>
he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ede thee as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his body, although thou haſt ſomewhat eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thy ſelfe; returne, returne, and refuſe not your owne good.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>He deſpiſeth God who takes that which belongeth to his Prince.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="4">4 Do not with ſcorne reiect his proffers, but prepare your troubled and ſcattred nunds to peace: for though fortune be now on your ſide, yet (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her wonted vnſteadfaſtnes) the caſe might change, and then your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines and good luck were ſoone deſtroid: euen as ſnow and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce melteth before the ſunne, euen ſo melteth proſperity when God will ſhew his anger: this is manifeſt, and dayly ſeene in diuers perſons in this exchaunging mortall life, yea in many kingdomes and countries, which are ſeene to fall through their owne default: It is folly to truſt on moueable things, if to day you are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, to morrow your ſtate may alter: and he that truſteth vpon himſelfe is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deceaued, before he doth imagine that the wind will blow againſt him. O <hi>Hollande</hi> bee not too proud, although thou art in a moment capſed vp to the toppe of fortunes wheele, for the foundation is naught, how ſure ſoeuer you thinke it.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Nothing can dure which hath no good ground.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="5">5 Thou art mercifully admoniſhed, but with crueltie thou ſtoppeſt thy eares, and your conceaued furie remaines ſo obſtinat that thou wilt not liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to any reaſon. Is there nothing that can abate your high minde, nor quench your bloody thirſt? the Omnipotent God doth perceaue your obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and how wilfully you hate peace: No doubt he will viſite thee: his hand doth threat thée, as not long ſince he hath miraculouſly ſhewen vnto thée, by the greate Whale which was ſeene at <hi>Scheueling</hi> vpon the ſtrand, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes like a thunder did burſt with great rumor &amp; bloodſhed. Marke and ruminate vpon this, as an eſpeciall token, and thinke that this dooth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſome wondrous thing. Let each one that heares this, take warning thereby. And if thou canſt taſte truth take warning hereout. Open thy eyes and vnlock thy ſtony hearts.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>God alwaies doth warne before he doth puniſh.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="6">6 Thou art threatned, thats a thing manifeſtly knowne: for each one can iudge what ſuch monſters betoken. Gods mightie and heauy hande is ouer your heads to plague you: with griefe and miſerie he will feade thée, yea with aduerſity, ruine and pouerty. Thy ioy he will conuert to ſorrow, thy laughing to laments, thy riches to nothing, as is ſeene: he altereth kingdomes: &amp; that which ſtandes high he doeth abaſe. This will befall thee vnleſſe thou wilt
<pb facs="tcp:7702:3"/>
acknowledge thy ſoueraigne as good ſubiects. Sheath thy murthering blate, let peace ſhine in thy heart before your deſtinies fall. Thy neighbours of whome you hope to reape comfort, and vpon whoſe alliance you ſo peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily ſtande will forſake thee, for euery one looketh to himſelfe when they are in néede. Of this aſſure your ſelues, for it is no fable.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>It is commonly ſaid, Daunger parteth friendſhip.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="7">7 Your bad pretences do war againſt God: ye are as in ſpite of nature it ſelfe: although other princes doe their profite with thée, yet (notwithſtanding) they hate theſe your trickes, thinking their ſubiects might alſo rebell: &amp; reiect their magiſtrates: for ſoone are founde many colours to reuolt, when once the minde is that way bent, your regiment is ſcandalous to all nations that know it, becauſe you deſpiſe ſuperiority: for they that reiect their Princes (ſaith S. <hi>Paule</hi>) withſtande Gods ordinance: you are like vnto the monſter which to the amazement of each one came beatles vpon the ſhore of <hi>Scheue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and there (to your learning) remained drie vpon the lande: wherefore learne obedience before the puniſhment come: for this ſame looking glaſſe was not planted in vaine.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Where grace is, there is alwaies time to repent.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="8">8 Yet for all this I imagine you will mocke at this admoniſhment, and (as you are wont) ſay it is nothing but the prating of Friers, or babling of Nuns: No medicines wil ſerue to your ſore, for alwaies the malicious mocks with Gods ſecrets: True it is, we are neither prophets nor children of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: we are far remoued from the knowledge of the diuine hidden ſecretes: yet our admoniſhment is not without foundation: beleeue if it ſo pleaſe you, for of pure zeale we open vnto you your eſtate: a wonderful change is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you: chooſe the beſt while you haue time, you are warned by the higheſt Regent. Giue place to reaſon, you are expected with grace. O Noble <hi>Holland</hi> quench your turbation. Ioyne with your bretheren: follow the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaile of friends and beléeue no ſtrife makers which will ruine you.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Vnwiſe is he that followes a blind mans trace.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="license">
               <p>Is ſéene and allowed to be printed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Datum Bruxellae <date>12. Martij. 1598.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Petrus Vinck Louannij,</signed>
                  <signed>Ioannes Maſius excudebat.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:4"/>
            <head>The Anſwere of the Hollanders to the ſeduced <hi>Prouinces vpon the former Admonition.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the firſt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>DIuinely and manly Noble <hi>Holland</hi> is exalted, for God doth of his mercy accept the ſame as his childe: beſides the defence of our pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fréedome, is the roote from whence nobility ſpringes: Theſe vrge vs Hollanders, and not the blind idolatrous Goddeſſe, whome wee refer to them that doe ſerue her. <hi>Prouidentia</hi> is our leader, for we finde that ſhe doth exalt vs aboue all eſtates. Such as ſooth vp their enemies, and hate their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. Iudge if they bee not to be eſteemed as wanton fooles: Thie is our meaning to endeauour to withſt and you andour enemies with force and ſtrength: And we will, to the ende, as long as neede ſhall require defend our common libertie doth daye and night, whileſt God giues vs ſtrength to abide it to fight for our ſelues and our neighbours who feede their deadly foe in their boſome, which is a dangerous and pittifull thing.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>For no Chriſtian is he that doth bad, and to ſtrengthen others therin.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the firſt.</head>
                  <p>YOu blinde Netherlanders reproch vs that wee haue quite forgot the band of amitie: neyther hath blood, murther, nor fire poſſeſſed our harts, neyther do we acknowledge <hi>Mars</hi> otherwiſe then for a blinde idoll, but onely the God of boaſt who hath imprinted in our hearts a ſtedfaſt thought of reconcilement, and peace, as well appeares by diuers our mintes, who out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardely ſhew our inwarde minde: we do our beſte to reioyne you, that are wrongfully ſeuered from vs, to the ende that the <hi>Spanyard</hi> do not hurt thee: for needefull defence of our libertie and goods is the rule of our pretences, and the bulwarke of our warre as long as Gods grace doth helpe vs, if we did otherwiſe we ſhould ſhame the Netherland blood. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs to be againſt Lyons and Foxes rauenous and crafte.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Simple as Doues, and ſuttle as Snakes.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the ſecond.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>YOu cannot compare vs to Beares or Wolues, who are full of crueltie ſuttle Foxes nor Dragons who long for bloud, for wee are tame as Lambes, guarded by Dogs, whoſe teeth defende vs from the wild beaſtes, (becauſe wee are reformed) ſuch is to vs not forbidden, we vſe it to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Our will, our ſéeking is that we do inuite, ſeeke and procure, through the commandement of Chriſt your ſafetie with ours both of bodie and ſoule: Our griefe is that you feele not your loſſe nor the dead: the cauſe of our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king armes is to defende our lawfull priuiledges, together with the libertie
<pb facs="tcp:7702:4"/>
of mind, and this is the only way to get the ſame, as in theſe our countries is apparantly to be ſeene, that this is the only marke we ſhout at, which we alſo will with deedes ſhew vnto you, if you will ioyne with vs, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the Spaniſh packe.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Whoſe pride is vnto God and man an horror.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the ſecond.</head>
                  <p>THe obedience which wee ſhew vnto our ſuperiours is willinglie without force, yea with iuſt deſire, as our contraries ſee and praiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it doe ſpite them, and ſhewes that we ſeeke nothing but to obay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the teaching of the wiſe: it appeares by that which we haue done, and ſuffered ſo long, for to remaine vnder the kings regiment as our Lorde but not as a tyrant: we could do no leſſe: we ſeeke but the libertie, which no Chriſtian Prince ought to refuſe to obedient Chriſtians, without the which we could not continue, nor be eſteemed good Chriſtians. For according to the ſcriptures (which we reade more then you do) for they are forbidden your ſights as a thing nothing touching your vocation: we finde that our faults are agréeing together, therefore he that is not content to doe miſchiefe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but exhorteth his neighbour alſo, their ambition verily ſheweth that God hath wholly pulled his grace from him.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>For God to the proud doth euer giue a fall.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the third.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>IN effect, we ſeeke to expell tyrannie, and with a ioyfull hart defend our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſoyle from your incurſions: and (through Gods helpe haue preſerued ſome part thereof to your good) hope to perſeuer further therein: wee neuer yet deſired to liue headleſſe, or without Magiſtrates, for wee account them vnwiſe which deſire it. But it is wiſedome to take a care thereof, and to haue Magiſtrates of our owne nation. As God hath alwaies exhorted his people. We ſtande not vpon our owne ſtrength, but with heart and mind put our whole truſt and defence in Gods handes. Our Prince we do not ſcorne, but feare the tyrant, who (according to Gods lawes) hath loſt his right. His en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties makes vs ſigh, perceiuing nothing in him, but the fruites of the ſick Lyon, to whom the Foxe for all his flatterie would giue no reliefe, for his deeds to others ſhew the intent of his heart.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>He that vſeth his right doth no body wrong.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the third.</head>
                  <p>YOur Prince calles and watches, as a Wolfe wounted lyeth a bedde, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting the Lambe to giue him ſome drinke, ſaying that afterwards he
<pb facs="tcp:7702:5"/>
would prouide meate himſelfe. To whome the ſilly Lambe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: yea marrie you would make me your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de: I per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your drift So the remembrance of his Lyon-like and Wolfe-like crueltie, doth make vs to eſteeme his calling, and entreating of no worthe: you boaſt much of his goodneſſe: you marke not the place nor perſon to whom you ſpeake, where ſcarce there is a ſteppe but his crueltie hath bene ſhowen, to what ende will you excuſe him? he hath manifeſtly ſhewed the ſame lately at Bruſſels vpon the body of a ſilly mayden. Why? you ſpeake it to <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who yet ſmell the fire of their late deſtruction of goods and blood, yea whoſe woundes are yet bleeding, his mercie which hath ſhewed vs his ſword, fire, and halter, neuer yet did he reach vs a fatherly hand, and yet he beares a very ſmooth face: but as the old Prouerbe ſayeth, which teacheth vs.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>He hath or will deceiue him where he can.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the third.</head>
                  <p>WE can ſoone iudge what mercie wee ſhould finde at the handes of him, who eſteemeth his highnes wronged in the higheſt degree for theſe foure poynts againſt his maieſtie. As <hi>Armes againſt him, new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to be ſworne againſt him: traffiking with other Potentates.</hi> Do you call this but ſome what eſtranged? what mercie can we expect of him who eſteemeth the reſignement of a ſmall requeſt of ſtate a great diſgrace to his highneſſe. He whome with vnmercifull tyrannie hath not vſed (the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. <hi>Weſt Indian</hi> Amercians, together with the wronged countries of <hi>Granada</hi> and <hi>Arragon</hi>) as ſubiects, but more like a rauening Wolfe, and all becauſe they had but deſired their wonted libertie, their teares could not mooue his ſtony &amp; wretched heart, but other hardened the ſame: what can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs not to be vſed in like ſort. Wherfore we truſt in our God, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt will ſtrengthen vs, vpon him as vpon a firme rock is our warre grounded.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Againſt God, neyther money, counſell, nor friends can p. euaile.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the fourth.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>NEuer Letter or meſſenger hath bene ſent to vs, but they haue ben read, and euery word vnderſtood and anſwered: inſomuch that they might well perceiue that wee ſought nothing better then a good peace. <hi>Hartius</hi> with his can witnes the ſame your idolatrous fortune (where with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in your admoniſhment you there twice threatned vs) we eſteeme her not a figge. Let Heathens and their like adore her, we acknowledge the ſtedfaſt prouidence of God, who altereth the kingdomes. Them that haue taken their dwelling places in the heanens, and made their neſtes in the clowdes. To his will and not to fortune do we giue the honour, where vnder onelie
<pb facs="tcp:7702:5"/>
do we ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our ſelues. This is ſéene by the Spaniſh king your Lord, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if he had taken this for a warning ſhould neuer haue come to this his diuliſh pride, whereby he hath greately begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to deſcend.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>God ſtrikes downe the proud, and rayſeth the humble.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the fourth.</head>
                  <p>THe chiefeſt things which do ruine a kingdome are, idolatrie, which of God is hated: tyranny to their ſubiects, &amp; wrong to their neighbours: for theſe offences doth God puniſh kingdomes: but <hi>Holland</hi> ſhall yet reioyce, and as a lambe ſtanding vpon Gods towre, laughes at the Wolfes threates, being aſſured that nothing can hurt him. What token, what fruite of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whereof you boaſt canſt thou ſhew vs of his mercifull déedes, &amp; yet lately you would haue murthered our Prince: theſe be your diſſembling admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: away away with them. The vnquenchable blood thirſt of thoſe diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh graſhoppers your Ieſuites, ye cuffians who gouerne your King, do teach vs not to truſt your diſſembling words.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The kingdome grounded vpon murther cannot ſtand.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More vpon the fift.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>WE haue bin often cruelly awakened when we did not ſleepe, that thoſe which were awakened neuer roſe againe, inſomuch that they that heard the knocks were aſtoniſhed, yet neuer had we any warning thereof by thoſe that could haue ſent it vs. But of you who acknowledge to haue no ſtrength, becauſe you are bent vnder the Spaniſh yoke, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour whoſe force is encloſed by the Spaniſh Counſaile, and ſhewe their commiſſions to pleaſure their mayſters: therfore it is good to admoniſh where one may haue thankes for it: but our eare is ſo ſurely ſtopt that we can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare, for wee haue <hi>Batauam aurem,</hi> an eare which is thicke, which will not be tempted, but as the Snake goeth ſubtilly, ſtopping her eares to the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiuers note, ſo will we not harken to your Syren-like words.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The birders whiſtle is ſweete, when the birds he will intrapt.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the fift.</head>
                  <p>GOd (for a while) hath fatherly chaſtiſed vs, both to puniſh vs &amp; to rue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine vs, and not alone perceauing our ſins, but alſo our miſeries, which alwaies haue cryed vengance vnto heauen vpon the Spaniards heads, who (as it ſeemeth of his mercy) hath heard our clamors. If God did propheſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing by the whale which appeared vpon our ſhore: what that may beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken we know not, for it may well be ſuch things may come to paſſe without any ſignification, much leſſe know wee what God doth hereby meane: yet your expoſition as full ſelfe wiſe ſecréetes wee eſteeme too fooliſh and raſh: but we doe not wonder, for the text of the matter is either falſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb facs="tcp:7702:6"/>
vnto you, or by you falſly contriued, for the fiſh was not headleſſe, as in your ſeuenth verſe you ſay, but contraryly he had more head then was proportionable to his bodie, the ſame being meaſured: but what may this ſignifie.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>For Gods tokens commonly threaten Gods enemies.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the fifth.</head>
                  <p>Nowe this is our expoſition which you cannot comprehende. This Whale is the greate Spaniſh Leuiathan, for he and the fiſh in nature are like, for as that fiſh of other fiſhes is the deuourer, ſo he alſo of other kingdomes is the deuourer and deſtroyer. The fiſhes head was aboue his proportion, and ſo is the Spaniarde, vnſatiably gréedie to ouer-gape all, though it coſt him his life. It is manifeſt in <hi>England, France,</hi> and the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandes: By the Whales burſting is meant that the Spaniard directing his force towardes <hi>England,</hi> for to ſubdue that with his neighbors, is there alſo runne aground, burſt and ſpoyled, to the ioy of all, and eſpecially of vs, who hope that God will cauſe him to runne himſelfe dead, if he will not ceaſe to perſecute the innocent.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>He that perſecutes another doth often fall himſelfe in trouble.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the ſixt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>IF euer there was any people threatned and croſſed by their enemies it is we, and by you watched, wherefore we reiect your ſugred wordes, which you began with vs euen againſt God, as by your vnaduiſe expoſition of the fiſh which was driuen vpon our ſhore, without hurt or daunger to anie: yea which is more, was profite for the country, wherefore we eſteeme that Gods tokens and threats are more ſtronger then many Wolues and Beares, who both hurt men and cattell, the ſwarming multitudes of dying beaſtes, who vexe &amp; deſtroy the fruits of trees &amp; growth of the earth: they are moſt Gods plagues. So that this fiſh paſſeth without propheſying any puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vs.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>But Gods wrath ouer them that ſeeke to hurt vs.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the ſixt.</head>
                  <p>WE acknowledge and confeſſe that wee haue deſerued Gods iuſt puniſhment, but we hope that his wrath will perſecute the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes vntill ſuch time as they leaue perſecuting the iuſt. The example wee ſhall ſée vpon thée O King, who wert rayſed to the top of the cloudes ſhalt fall downe without ſtay vntill thou acknowledge God in his force. We haue long ynough to the loſſe of our bloud helde him for our Prince, till at length we haue reiected him and forſworne his allyance, which pure néede hath cauſed, the verdite whereof we remit vnto our Lord God. Vpon <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; <hi>France</hi> we will not boaſt, the humaine arme is weake &amp; to no effect:
<pb facs="tcp:7702:6"/>
but God is our, fortreſſe and that we conioyne with our neighbours, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are coparteners with vs in like woes, is no ſhame, and their reuolt with your threats doth not make vs ſhrinke.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The feare of common ruine bindes friendſhip faſter.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the ſeuenth.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>IDolatry doth warre againſt Gods learning, and that you reproch vs. God and nature doth ordaine Princes for their ſubiects defence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, when now the Prince through enuie and tyrannie doth abuſe his power, and his vaſſalles, then doeth God take away from him the vertue and right which he had giuen him by nature, yet not all princes, but thoſe that ſuppreſſe their people with iniuſtice. <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> are out of thy reproch, for their kinde gouernement commendes our déeds. The ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall which you ſpake of haue we not giuen: but if any hypocrite doth ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize himſelfe, it is his owne folly, to trouble himſelfe with that which is not worth a myte. You alſo doe call vs rebelles: whereof we are comforted long ſince, for our patience doth chaunge the minds of diuers, who offer vs of loue a furthering hand.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>If ſo be we do not herden our ſelues to beginne miſchiefe</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the ſeuenth.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that according to their countrie lawes do defend their countries right, are lawfull Magiſtrates, which wee not refuſe, nor yet reiects them, as you ſpitefully reproch vs. We reſiſt the tyrant, according to the iudgement of any, yet doe we not tranſgreſſe the ordinances of God: neyther do we reiect the admonition of S. <hi>Paule.</hi> But the word of God teacheth that lawfull magiſtrates are placed by him to keepe their people in peace and quietneſſe and to chaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the wicked: When now they beginne with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous ſuggeſtions to opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe their ſubiects, with iuſt cauſe may they bee depoſed, as breakers of theſe contractes, and their ſubiectes are not baunde to ſhew them any more obedience. Becauſe nowe this Spaniarde is like vnto the monſter in euerie degrée: we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e flie his bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thirſtie tirranny.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Vnwiſe is he to ſeeke mercie where none is to be found.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon the eight.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>THe vnaduiſed diſcourſe, fiered out of the mouth of a madde man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground or meaning is mocked and ſcoffed at euery where, as foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh wordes, but they that be any way allyed vnto him by kinred or friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that do loue him, are grieuouſly ſorry, for thereby they know the vncurable madneſſe where withall he is poſſeſt. Euen thus is it with vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, who mocks others, giuing vs no other hope to cure your mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:7702:7"/>
you are wholly vnapt to take good counſaile: we loue trueth, but your fayned diſcourſe interlarded with diuerſitie of fine phraiſed lyes, doth make vs aſſure our ſelues, that either you are poſſeſſed with madneſſe, or with Spaniards, to yours and our ruine, and deſtruction of your patrimonie.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>He that perſueth ruine, ſhall ſoone ouertake it.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>More vpon the eight.</head>
                  <p>YOur accuſation is better: your admoniſhment to peace and obedience is without grounde. That you do it of pure zeale we beléeue the ſame alſo: But your zeale is fooliſh and blinde: you ſay that a wonderfull chaunge is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for vs, this you grounde vpon your peace with the French Nation: What more hurtful mutation can befal then to be in a league with Wolues? But if you are no Prophets, whithertended then your oration, for the Lambe for although he had pleadges dares not commit himſelfe to the Wolues mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, he rather would deuour both Lambe and pledges, then hee would let the Lambe liue. We know the decrée giuen in the Popes Councell: <hi>That one ought not to keepe faith vnto heretickes.</hi> We haue ſéene it in manie to whome it hath coſt their liues. But indeede you haue your wiſh, ioyning your dédes with ours, not liſting to ſtrife-makers: for he is vnwiſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes his friends his enemies.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>And a more foole is hee, who his foes for friends takes to be.</p>
                     <bibl>Vigilanria &amp; fidei 1598.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed at Amſterdam for Laurence Iacobs Stationer, vpon the water in the bible.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles and conditions of the peace and perpetuall lyance concluded betweene the high and Mightie Princes PHILLIP <hi>by the grace of God, Catholike King of Spaine &amp;c.</hi> And HENRY the Fourth of that name by the ſame grace moſt Chriſtian King of France Anno 1598.</head>
            <head type="sub">Whereunto are annexed the Articles of the Peace concluded in the Caſtle of Cambreſii, Anno 1559. betweene the Catholike King of Spaine, &amp; the late Henry the ſecond moſt Chriſtian King of France.</head>
            <byline>Firſt tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lated out of French into Dutch, and now into our vulgar tongue by H. W. In the name of God the Creator.</byline>
            <p>BE it knowen vnto all men preſent, and to come, that as the Realme of <hi>France</hi> &amp; the Netherl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndiſh Prouinces, haue endured great loſſe &amp; da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, by reaſon of the ciuill and forraigne warres, who haue continued theſe many yeares, which the kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7702:7"/>
the countries of <hi>Sauoy</hi> haue well knowne and felt, while in the meane time the common enemie to Chriſtendome and the Chriſtian name, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his welfare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ruine, procuring to ſurmount vs through our ſtrife, hath gotten a perilous procéeding, in his vnlawfull ſuggeſtion of the Chriſtian Prouinces, the which being conſiddered by our Holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Clemene</hi> the eight of that name, and deſiring with all diligence to Preuent the ſame, and to cut aſunder the roote of this miſchiefe, and hath through his Meſſenger dwelling at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a drill, and other doone, and pronounced diuers demonſtrations, and exhortations vnto the high and mighty Prince <hi>Phillip</hi> the ſecond, by the grace of God Catholike king of <hi>Caſtile, Aragon, Leno,</hi> and both citties of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> of <hi>Portingall</hi> and <hi>Granada</hi> &amp;c. to the end to bring him vnto an amiable peace and accorde, with the moſt high &amp; mightie Prince. <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth by the ſame grace moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauare,</hi> vnto whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s holines had ſent the illuſtrous and reuerend Cardinall of <hi>Florence Alexander de Medicis</hi> Legatte to him and to the Apoſtolique Seate, to pronounce like exhortations vnto the ſaide moſte Chriſtian kinge, and according as our ſaide Holy Father hath béene aduertiſed that the ſaide Catholike kinge had giuen full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and inſtruction to conclude this peace vnto the high &amp; mightie prince <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> Cardinall, Arch Duke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> his nephew, and alſo for the greate good truſte which be had in him, and affection which he hath alwaies had to the ſaid peace, had ſent vnto him the reuerent Father <hi>I. Bonauenture Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agirono.</hi> Generall of the order of S. <hi>Frances,</hi> to the ende he might by him vnderſtand his meaning in this matter, and alſo to giue him further know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the meaning of the ſaide Catholike king touching this peace, hauing preſented all what is aforeſaid vnto the ſaid moſt chriſtian king according to the order which he had receaued of his holines, the ſaid kings incited through a godly zeale, pitty and griefe which they conceaued and felt in their hearts, of the long heauie and burthenſome miſerie, which through continuance of the ſaid wars their kingdomes, countries and ſubiects haue and yet endure: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ending not to let ſlip an occaſion which conſiſteth in the power of God fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Princes, and that loue their ſubiects, to bring and perpetually place an aſſured peace and tranquility in this land, and eſpecially in the prouinces ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he which it hath pleaſed God to conſtitute them as their kéepers and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and déepely conſidering (as their duty is) the graue and wiſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions and exhortations of our ſaid holy father, and being therevpon agréede haue requeſted their friendes, and allies, with them to vnderſtand and reſolue a good peace and vnion, to the reſt and quietnes of all the Chriſtian prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to the reuiuing and tranquility of all the ſubiectes, and to beginne the ſaide treatie haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appointed, to wit by the ſaide Cardinall arch Duke,
<pb facs="tcp:7702:8"/>
for and in the name of the ſame catholike king, and by vertue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power which he hath of his maieſtie. The Lord <hi>Iohn Richardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> knight &amp; head preſident of the priuy counſale of eſtate, the Lord <hi>Iohn Baptiſt de Taxis</hi> knight commander in the <hi>Saintes</hi> of the war like order of S. <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp; of the ſaide counſaile of eſtate, and counſaile of the war: and the Lord <hi>Lewis Verey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> knight audiencier. and chiefe Secretary, and Treſurer of the <hi>Briefs</hi> and of the foreſaid counſaile of eſtate, and of the ſide of the moſt chriſtian king, the Lord <hi>Pomponius de Bellieure</hi> knight, Lord of <hi>Grigon,</hi> Counſaylor of his counſaile of eſtate, and the Lord <hi>Nicholas Bruſlart,</hi> knight, Lord of <hi>Sildeny</hi> alſo Counſaylor of the ſaid king in his counſaile of eſtate and Preſident in the court of Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> all furniſhed with ſufficient power, the which at the end herof ſhalbe inferred, which lords deputies by vertue of their power in profe of the ſaid Cardinall who hath long time laboured to the furthering of this preſent peace, haue concluded &amp; agreed vpon theſe articles following.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inprimis it is concluded and agreed, that the treatie of peace ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue reſolued and concluded, betwéene the Lords, Kings, <hi>Phillip</hi> the 2. and <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. confirming in approbation of the articles comprehended in the treatie of Peace made vpon the caſtell of <hi>Cambreſis</hi> in the yeare 1559. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſaid Catholike K. <hi>Phillip</hi> the 2. and of high and lautable memory <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> all which ſaid treatie the ſaid deputes haue againe newlie confirmed and ratified in all poyntes, in ſuch order as if it were her inferred, from word to word without renewing any thing in the ſame nor in any other before, which all ſhall continue whole and entire, except that which ſhalbe annulled in this preſent treaties.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And according to the ſame, that from the date of theſe preſents betwéene the ſaid Lords, Kings, their children preſent and to come, their heires and ſucceſſors, their kingdomes, countries, and ſubiectes, ſhall be a good, ſure, ſtable, and inuiolable peace, confederation, eternall alliance and friendſhip, ſhall alſo loue one an other like brethren, ſéeking and procuring with all duty the others welfare, honor and reputation, and ſhall faithfully ſhun (for ſo much as ſhall be poſſible) the one the others hurt, not entertayning nor fauoring any perſons whatſoeuer, which ſhould be any waies ſubiect to the hurte or damage, of the one or the other, and ſhall from this day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ceaſe all enmity, forgetting from this day all thinges, that may haue béene euill done how and whatſoeuer they be, they ſhall put in obliuion and annuled without at any time after the ſame ſhal be any wais rayſed, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, reiecting by this preſent treatie, al practiſes, or inteligences which in any ſorte ſhould be to the detriment, the one of the other: alſo promiſing not to do, perſue nor procure through any to be done any thing that might tend to the hurt the one to the other, not alſo ſuffer that their ſubiects ſhal either
<pb facs="tcp:7702:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectly or indirectly do the ſame, and if ſo be any of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of what qualitie or condition ſoouer, ſhould from the date hereof chance to doe any thing to the contrarie, eyther by ſea or land, or otherwiſe aſſiſt or helpe in matters that might be any waie hurtefull vnto the ſaide Lordes, Kings, the other ſhall be bounde to oppoſe him ſelfe there againſt and hinder the ſame, and ſeuerely to puniſh them as breakers of this peace, &amp; diſturbers of the common quietnes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And through vertue of this peace and amitie, the ſubiects of both ſides whatſoeuer they are, ſo far forth they kéepe the lawes and cuſtomes of the countrie ſhalbe ſuffered, to go, come, remaine dwell, conuerſe and returne in the one and others countrie, vſing the trade of merchandiſe, or as beſt ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike them, as well by ſea as by land, and vpon the freſh waters frequent and trade together, and the ſaid ſubiectes ſhall be defended in paying reaſonably the rightes and duties in al places vſed, and others which by their maieſties, or their ſucceſſors ſhall be impoſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And all letters of repriualles which might haue bene giuen for what cauſe ſoeuer ſhalbe ſuſpended, and from this day forwarde there ſhalbe none more giuen, by any of the ſaid Princes to the preiudice of the others ſubiects, except onely againſt the chiefe offendours, their goods and of their complices and that yet in caſe of manifeſt denegation of iuſtice, of which &amp; of the letters of reformation &amp; requiſition of thoſe which ſhal purſue the ſaid letters repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uals ſhalbe bound to make appeare in maner &amp; forme as iniuſtice is required.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The citties, ſubiects cittizens and inhabitantes of the counties of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Artoiis,</hi> &amp; other Prouinces of <hi>Netherland,</hi> together with the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall enioy the Priuiledges, and freedomes which haue béene granted betweene the kinges of <hi>Frances</hi> prediceſſors of the ſaid moſt Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian King: and alſo the citties ſubiects, and cittizens and inhabitantes of the kingdome of <hi>France</hi> ſhall likewiſe enioy the liberties and freedomes which they haue in the ſaid low countries and kingdomes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and as euerie one of them hath heretofore enioyed them, &amp; as they doe enioy them by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the treatie of the yeare 1559. and other precedents.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Alſo it is couenanted and agréede, that if in caſe the ſaide King Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like do geue or tranſfer by teſtament, or what title ſoeuer it be vnto the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Princes the Lady <hi>Iſabella</hi> his eldeſt daughter or to any other the prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Lowcountries with the counteſſe of <hi>Burgondy</hi> and <hi>Charlois,</hi> that all the ſaid Prouinces and counties do vnderſtande to bée comprehended in this preſent treatie as they were in that of <hi>anno.</hi> 1559. together with the ſaide Princes or he to whome in fauour the ſaid king Catholique ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſame without being néedefull that to this effect there ſhould be made a new treatie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And may returne the ſubiects and ſeruantes of the one ſide and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:7702:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the which they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ided before the end of <hi>December</hi> 1588. except Eccleſiaſtical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which ſhould be found to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally prouided together with the enioying of each and euery one their good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and perpetuall ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, which they by rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> begin in the end of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de yeare of 1588. haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enioye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> receaued, ſhall now againe vſe ande may after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this peace, and in like ſort of thoſe which ſince the ſaide time may be dew vnto them by right of ſucceſſion or otherwiſe without any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but notwithſtanding without any right to demand of thoſe which haue poſſeſſed the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oueable goods, the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and benefites procéeded th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſaide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vntill the publication of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe preſente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor alſo the debts which haue builde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the ſaide time, and ſhall be helde for good &amp; valliable the reparation which the Prince, his Lieu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tennant, or deputy hath or ſhall doe vnder the iuriſdiction of whome the ſaid a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſt ſhall be made, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may any creditor of the ſaide deptes or any their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyes neuer bée receaued to purſue the ſaid deptes, in what order or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe to whome the ſaid giftes haue bene made nor againſt thoſe that by vertue of ſuch gifts &amp; confiſcations haue paide them, for what raiſes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſaid deptes may be, notwithſtanding any bils of obligation which the ſaide deptes may be, notwithſtanding any bils of obligation which the ſaide creditors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght haue therof, the which through effect of the ſaid con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar &amp; ſhall remaine by this preſent treatie, cancelled, ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led &amp; without feare.</p>
            <p n="8">8 And the ſaid ſubiects and ſeruants of both ſides ſhall returne vnto their ſaid vnmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eable goods &amp; rents aforeſaid notwithſtanding at gifts con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>embs, declarations, confiſcations, &amp; commiſſons ſentences reneued by continuance and in abſence of the parties, and thoſe not heard by of the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, which ſentences &amp; all iudgements giuen as well in ciuill as crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall matters ſhal remaine voyde and of no worth as if they had not bene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, thereof wholy encreaſing the ſaide ſubiects, ceaſing all hindrances and contradictions vnto the rightes which they had at the time of the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſaide warre without that any one may be charged for charges publike or entermiſes which he had how beit for the victuals, maintainment of money, or otherwiſe during the time &amp; occaſion of the ſaid warres, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſhould haue made account vnto ſuch as then had power to diſpoſe thereof, ſo far foorth that the ſaid ſubiects and ſeruants be not founde guiltie of any other crimes, then to haue ſerued in contrary party, and not neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, retire themſelues into the countries and Lordſhips of the ſaid kings without they haue firſt thereof obtayned permiſſion, and letters patents ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the great ſeale of their Maieſtie the which they ſhalbe bound to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
<pb facs="tcp:7702:9"/>
before Commiſſioners and officiate of their ſaid matter.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Thoſe which ſhould haue bene prouided by the one or the other ſide with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny benefices, ſtanding to the collation, preſentation, or vther diſpoſition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſaid Lords, Kings, or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aymen ſhal remaine in the poſſeſſion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of the ſaid benefices as be well and duly prouided.</p>
            <p n="10">10 In fauor &amp; regard of this peace, and to the end that the ſaid Princes giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntentment one to another, is concluded and agreed, that they ſhal render and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtore the one to the other effectually &amp; in pure faith, that which ſhalbe found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o haue bene taken, feiſed, and occupied by them, or others hauing any charge of them or in their name, in each others countrie, vz. the ſaide moſt chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſhall render vnto the ſaid king Catholike, the puſſance and poſſeſſion of the countie of <hi>Charlois,</hi> his appurtenances, &amp; dependances, to ioyne the ſame by him and his ſucceſſors wholy and peaceably and retaine the ſame vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueraintie of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; if it be founde that any place, haue bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciſed ſince the ſaid Peace of <hi>anno</hi> 59. by the ſaid moſt chriſtian King, or his ſhal alſo be reſtored, and all within the tearme of two moneths to recken from the day and date of theſe preſentes.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And likewiſe the Catholike king ſhall render and reſtore vnto the moſte chriſtian King thoſe places which ſhall be found to be taken by him or his ſince the ſaid peace made in the caſtel in <hi>Cambreſis.</hi> vz. <hi>Calis, Ardres, Monthul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Dourlens, La Chappel in Le Chaſtelet in Picardie, Blauet in Britanie</hi> &amp; all other places which the ſaide catholike king, eyther there or in any other places of <hi>France</hi> detaineth ſince the ſaid treatie.</p>
            <p n="12">12 As for <hi>Calis Ardres, Monthullen, Dourlens, Chappell, &amp; Le Chaſteller,</hi> they ſhalbe rendred by the ſaid catholike king, or his deputies, effectually and in good faith, without any prologatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or difficulty for what occaſion or pretence ſoeuer, vnto him or them, who ſhalbe thereunto deputed &amp; ordained by the ſaide moſt chriſtian king within two moneths preciſely to account from the day and date of theſe preſents in the ſtate wherin they are at this preſent, without brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, weaking or endam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging them in any ſorte, &amp; without pretending nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding any remburſement, for the fortifications, made in the foreſaid places nether for the pay which might be due vnto the ſouldiers or men of war there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding &amp; in the aforeſaide reſtitution ſhall firſt be deliuered the cittie of <hi>Calis, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> &amp; the reſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> following in ſuch fort that the foreſaid reſtitution ſhall wholy be effected in the ſaid tearme of two moneths.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Touching the reſtitution of <hi>Blauet</hi> the ſame ſhal alſo in good faith be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually without any prolongation, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficultie for what cauſe ſoeuer executed vnto thoſe who ſhalbe thereunto appoynted by the ſaid moſt chriſtian king, and that within 3. moneths after the date of theſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; the ſame Catholik king may cauſe to be broken down the fortifications by him or his made in the ſaide <hi>Blauet</hi> and other places which ſhalbe by him rendred in <hi>Britanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb facs="tcp:7702:10"/>14 Reſtitution being made of the ſaid places the ſaid king catholike may cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be carried away all the artillary, Bullets, armour, victuals and other muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians of warre which ſhalbe founde in the ſaid places at the time of the reſtitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, alſo it ſhalbe ſuffered vnto the ſouldiers and other people, which ſhal depart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of theſe places to carrie away all their goods and moueables vnto them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partayning, without that it be lawfull to aske any thing of the inhabitants of the ſaid places or plain or flat countries, nor any wiſe to endamage their houſes, or to take any thing away from the ſaid inhabitants.</p>
            <p n="15">15 And to the ende that the ſouldiers remayning in the ſame <hi>Blauer,</hi> may conueniently depart toward <hi>Spaine,</hi> the aforeſaid moſt Chriſtian king wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhips &amp; marriners, in which veſſels they may lade their artillerie, victuals and other munitions of war with their baggage, they in the aforeſaide <hi>Blauet,</hi> &amp; other rendred places in <hi>Britaine</hi> in giuing ſecurity of reſtitution of the ſaid veſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls &amp; conuay of the ſaid marriners w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the tearme which ſhalbe ordained.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Moreouer the ſaid deputiſe promiſe, for ſecurity of reſtitution of the ſaide places as ſoone as this preſent treatie ſhould be ratified by the moſt chriſtian K. to deliuer 4. pledges, ſuch as he will chooſe, ſubiects vnto the ſaid Catholike K. the which ſhalbe honorably kept &amp; entertayned as their qualities require. The reſtitution being made and really accompliſhed, the ſaid pledges ſhalbe rendred and ſet at liberty, in good faith without any delay, but muſt be vnderſtoodde that after the accompliſhment of the 6. places in <hi>Picardy,</hi> but two of the ſaid pledges ſhalbe deliuered remayning the other two vntil the reſtitution of <hi>Blauet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 And for the matter contayned in the aforeſaide treatie of 1559. which wer not accordingly executed, the ſame ſhal now be wholy executed &amp; ended, in that which reſts aſwel reſpect of the county of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> the limets of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the ſaid two Princes which he held in ſurueyans and exemption of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and forraigne impoſition pretended by theſe of the county of <hi>Burgundy</hi> Biſhop <hi>Therouane,</hi> the abby of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> at the mountaine of the Ducchie of <hi>Bouilon,</hi> reſtitution of any pretended places of the one ſide and the other ought to be rendred, by vertue of the ſaid treatie, and the other differences which haue not bin voide or decided, as it was then couenanted there ſhall to this effect be na-Arbitrators of the one &amp; the other part the which ſhal méet within 6. months in the appoynted place if the parties conſent, els ſhal choſe ſome other place.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And as in the partition of the countries ordayned vnto the Biſhopriks of <hi>Arras, Amiens,</hi> S. <hi>Omer</hi> and <hi>Boloigne</hi> are founded certaine villages of <hi>France</hi> attributed vnto the Biſhops of <hi>Afras,</hi> and S. <hi>Omer.</hi> Alſo other villages of the countries of <hi>Artoyes</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> vnto the Biſhop of <hi>Amiens</hi> and <hi>Bologne</hi> whence often riſeth diſcorde and confuſion, is couenanted and agréed that after the conſent of our holie father the Pope: commiſſioners ſhall be appoynted by the one and the other ſide which ſhall aſſemble within a yeare in ſuch places as ſhalbe appoynted, to reſolue vppon the chaunge which may be done of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:7702:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſages, to the commodity of the one and the other ſide.</p>
            <p n="19">19 All priſoners of war being detayned by them or either party ſhalbe ſet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bertie, in paying their charges, and that which otherwiſe they may lawfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w, without paying any ranſom, except they had thereof agréed before the date <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f theſe preſets &amp; if in caſe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint be made of the exceſſe therof, there ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e taken order by the Prince of the countrie wher the ſaid priſonersar detained.</p>
            <p n="20">20 And all other priſoners, ſubiects, vnto the aforeſaid Kings, which through the calamity of the warres may be detayned vppon the Gallies of their Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, ſhall immediatly be releaſed, and ſet at liberty without any delay, for what cauſe ſoeuer and without demanding of them any thing of their ranſomes, or their charges.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And are reſerued vnto the ſaid catholike king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp; the ſaid worthy Princeſſe his eldeſt daughter their ſucceſſors, or deputes, al their rights, actions, and pretentſons, which appertayne vnto them of the ſaid kingdomes, countries, lordſhips or others for what cauſe ſoeuer the which he nor his predeceſſors haue not bene expreſly renounced, thereof alſo to make purſute by amiable meanes or iuſtice and not with armes.</p>
            <p n="22">22 And in that which by the ſaid deputes of the ſaid catholike king is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated for to obtayne to a good and perfect peace, his maieſtie requeſteth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt excellent Prince the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> may be comprehended in the ſaide peace, becauſe the aforeſaid Catholike king doth tender the welfare of the ſaide Lord, Duke as his owne, for the great kinred of blood and neare alliance which is betwéene them, the which is alſo declared by this <hi>Gaſper</hi> of <hi>Geneua,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Bullen,</hi> Councellor of eſtate, Chamberlaine and Collonell of the guarde of the ſaid Lorde Duke, his Lieuetennant and gouernour of the Dutchie of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and the Cittie of <hi>Iurie,</hi> his Deputy, as appeareth by his power and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, who in honor of his name, ſaide that his ſaid Lord was iſſued from the brother of the great grandfather of the aforenamed moſt Chriſtian king, and of the couſin germaine of the Quéene his mother and that his intente is to giue contentment vnto the ſaid Lorde, king, &amp; as one of his moſt humble parentage, to acknowledge him with all the honor, duty, reuerence &amp; obſeruance of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hee may poſſibly, to the end to giue occaſion in the time to come to thinke better of him and his actions, the paſſed occaſions would ſuffer him the ſaid king promiſſing to acknowledge his good affection, and that he will vſe vnto him, of like bounty and declaration of friendſhip, as the 4. laſt kings haue vſed vnto the the late moſt excellent memorie of my Lord the Duke his father.</p>
            <p n="23">23 It is therefore agréed that the ſaide Duke ſhall be receiued &amp; comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this treatie of Peace. And to manifeſt the deſire which he hath to content the ſaid Chriſtian King, will render vnto him the Cittie &amp; caſtell of <hi>Berre,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 2. months to compt from the date of theſe preſents, in good faith and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without delay or difficultie for what cauſe ſo euer. And the ſaide place
<pb facs="tcp:7702:11"/>
ſhall be rendred to the ſaide king, within the ſaid tearme directly, in the eſtate wherein ſhe is at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, without breaking down, nor endomaging them in any wiſe, without that any remburſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the fortifications made in the ſaid cittie &amp; caſtell may any wiſe be pretended, neither for that which might be due vnto the ſoldiers &amp; men of war. Alſo leauing there al the ordinance which was there, at the taking of the ſame with the bullets, &amp; may onely withdraw thoſe which ſithence he brought thether, if any there be.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Alſo it is conuenanted and agréed that the ſaid Duke ſhall wholy diſauow &amp; abandon, in good faith, the Captaine <hi>la Fortune,</hi> being in the cittie of <hi>Suerre</hi> in the country of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> without giuing vnto him nor any other (which he vnlawfully detaineth the ſaide cittie againſt the will of the ſaid moſt chriſtian King) directly or indirectly any aide, ſupport or fauour.</p>
            <p n="25">25 And for the ſurplus of all other differences, the foreſaid moſt Chriſtian K. &amp; Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> the aforeſaid deputes, in the aforeſaid name, conſente &amp; agrée for the good of the peace, that they be remitted vnto the iudgement of our holie father the Pope, <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. for to be iudge &amp; decided by his holynes, within one year to account, from the day &amp; date of theſe preſents according vnto the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of the ſaid king giuen in writing the 4. of Iune laſt paſt, &amp; to kéep, execut, &amp; maintaine all what ſhalbe by his holines ordained, without delay, prolongati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or difficulty for what cauſe or pretence ſoeuer, &amp; meane while and vntill ſuch time theſe things be otherwiſe diſpoſed of by his holines, they ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emaine in the eſtate &amp; conditions, as at this preſent, without either changing or renewing, &amp; as they are poſſeſſed by the one, &amp; the other party, ſo ſhal it not be lawful to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or require any contribution nor other things without the territories of the places which are held by the one and by the other.</p>
            <p n="26">26 And therefore it is now couenanted &amp; agréed, by the one ſide and the other that from this day forwarde ſhalbe ſure peace betwéene the aforeſaid kings and duke, their children, preſent &amp; to come, heires, ſucceſſors, &amp; inheritors, their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes countries and ſubiects, without they may make any enterpriſe vpon the countries or ſubiects, the one of the other, for what cauſe or pretence ſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="27">27 The ſubiects and ſeruants of either ſide, aſwel eccleſiaſticall as ſecular not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they haue ſerued in contrary party, ſhal returne wholy in the poſſeſſion &amp; enioying of all and each their goods, offices and benefices, as haue bene ſaid aboue of the ſubiects and ſeruants of the ſaide kinges, but not to bée vnderſtood of the gouernements.</p>
            <p n="28">28 As for the priſoners of warre they ſhall bee vſed as is aboue written, and by the aforeſaid Princes is agréede.</p>
            <p n="29">29 And ar confirmed in all poynts &amp; articles the treatiſe hertofore made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the late moſt chriſtian K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. &amp; <hi>Charles</hi> the 2. &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. the ſaid deceaſed duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> in the year 1559. in the caſtel of <hi>Cambreſis,</hi> except ſuch things as are by this or other treatiſes annulled, &amp; accordingly the ſaid Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:7702:11"/>
               <hi>Sauoy</hi> his countries, citties, &amp; ſubiects ſhal continue a good newtral Prince and common friend, vnto both the ſaid kings, from the day of the publication of theſe preſents, the traffike betwéene this countries &amp; ſubiects, ſhalbe frée and aſſured as is ſaid in the ſaid treatiſe, and as in times paſt haue bene vſed, &amp; the poyntes therein comprehended ſhalbe obſerued in regard of the officiares who haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſaid kings ſo far forth it be not annulled by other accordes.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Are yet notwithſtanding reſerued vnto the ſaide moſt Chriſtian king of <hi>France,</hi> and his ſucceſſors all their rights, actions and pretentions which they know to appertaine vnto them by reaſon of the ſaid kingdoms, countries, lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, or others, for what cauſe or pretence ſoeuer, vnto the which ſhall not be neither by him or his predeceſſors, expreſely renounced, thereof to make purſute by friendly meanes of iuſtice, and not by armes.</p>
            <p n="31">31 In this peace and amity ſhalbe comprehended by common accord and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the aforeſaide moſt chriſtian king, &amp; catholike king, if ſo be they will bee comprehended in the ſame, &amp; chiefely on the ſide of the catholike king, our holie father the Pope, the Apoſtolike ſeate, the Emperor of the <hi>Romanies,</hi> the Lords the Arch Dukes, his brethren &amp; couſins, their kingdomes &amp; countries, the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors &amp; princes of the Citties &amp; eſtate of the holy Empire, vnder whoſe obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance the duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> the biſhoprike &amp; county of <hi>Liege,</hi> the ſea-bordering citties, &amp; counties of eaſt <hi>Freeſeland,</hi> &amp; the ſaid Princes ſhal renounce vnto alpractiſes &amp; promiſes neuer hereafter, to make an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eneither w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſtendom nether w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out, whenſoeuer, which may any wiſe be preiudicial vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid L. Emperor, elector or eſtates of the ſaid holy Empire, but to the contrary ſhal procure with all their power &amp; induſtry, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good &amp; quietnes thereof, ſo far forth that the ſaide Lords, Emperors and the ſaide eſtates, ſhal be haue themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miably vnto them, the ſaid kings catholike, and moſt chriſtian, and commit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in preiudice of them, and in like ſort ſhalbe comprehended in this Peace, the Lords, the conferats of the great citties of <hi>Germane,</hi> &amp; the lagues <hi>Griſes</hi> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> their allies, the K. of <hi>Polland</hi> &amp; <hi>Sweed,</hi> the K. of <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> the K. of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the Duke &amp; Signorie of <hi>Venice,</hi> the duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> the great duk of <hi>Thuſcane,</hi> the Republiques of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and <hi>Luca,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> &amp; <hi>Plaiſance,</hi> the Cardinall <hi>Farneſe</hi> his brother, the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> the chiefe of the houſes of <hi>Columna</hi> and <hi>Vrſine</hi> the Duke of <hi>Salamoneta,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Monaco,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Finall,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Maſla,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Plombin,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Sala,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Colorino.</hi> For to vſe and continue this preſent peace with exprſſe declaration that the aforenamed moſt Chriſtian Kinge may neither di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectely nor indirectely labour through himſelfe or others to preiudice: and it the ſame moſt Chriſtian Prince pretende any thing againſt them, may onely proſecut the ſame before co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent iudges &amp; not els in any manner whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="32">32 And on the behalfe of the moſt chriſtian king ſhalbe comprehended in this preſent treatie (if in caſe they therein will be comprehended, our Holie
<pb facs="tcp:7702:12"/>
Father the Pope the ſeae apoſtolique the Emperour, Elector, and Princes eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall and ſecular, cities, comminalties and eſtates of the holy Empire and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the country <hi>Pallatine</hi> Elector, the Marquis of <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Wittenbergh</hi> thee Landgraue of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> thee Marquis of <hi>Hamſbach,</hi> thee Earles of eaſt <hi>Freeſland,</hi> the Seabordering citties, according to the ancient al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, the king and kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> according to the aneient alliances &amp; confederations made betweene the kingdomes of <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> the kings of <hi>Poland, Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweede,</hi> the Duke and gouernors of <hi>Venice,</hi> the three Cantons of the leagues of <hi>Switſers,</hi> the Lordes of the 3 leagues <hi>Griſes,</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Lorde of the land of <hi>Vallay,</hi> the Abbote and Citie of S. <hi>Gall, Cloutem bergh Milhouſe</hi> the country <hi>Neufcaſtle,</hi> and other allies and confederates of the ſaide League, my Lord the Duke of <hi>Loraine,</hi> my Lorde the greate Duke of <hi>Thuſcane,</hi> my Lord the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> the Repuhlique of <hi>Luca,</hi> the Biſhops Chapters of <hi>Metz Tibold</hi> and <hi>Verden,</hi> the Abbote of <hi>Gozze,</hi> the <hi>SS.</hi> of <hi>Sedan,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Admirande,</hi> is to be vnderſtood notwithſtanding that the conſent which thee catholique king giueth in the comprehenſion of Eaſt <hi>Freeſland,</hi> bee without preiudice vnto the right which his Catholique Maieſtie hath ouer the countries thereof, like as contrariwiſe are reſerued, the differances, rightes and exemptions of the ſaide counties, al which declaration that the ſaide king catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, may neither directly nor inderectly labour through himſelfe or any other, to their preiudice, but if the aforeſaid catholike king pretend any thing againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may onely proſecute the ſame before competent iudges, &amp; not by force in what manner ſo euer.</p>
            <p n="33">33 Alſo ſhalbe comprehended in this preſent treatie all others, who by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent of the ſaide kinges may be choſen ſo farre foorth that within 6. monethes after the declaration of theſe preſentes they ſhall deliuer their obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie letters and declarations, as in ſuch caſes is required.</p>
            <p n="34">34 And for more ſecuritie of this peace and Articles theirin comprehended, ſhall the ſaide treatie be verefied, publiſhed, and regiſtred, in the courte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentes in the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; Chamber of accountes, of the ſaide cittie of <hi>Paris,</hi> as likewiſe verified, publiſhed &amp; regiſtred, in the great counſaile cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of accounts, of the catholike king in the Low countries, all according to the te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or of the treatie of <hi>anno.</hi> 1559. which ſhalbe diſpatched by the one &amp; the other ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, within 3. moneths after the publication of this preſent treatie.</p>
            <p n="35">35 In which poynts and articles aboue named, is fully comprehend the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and articles, which haue bene agréed and paſſed, betwéene the ſaid deputies, and in the names as is aforeſaide, the which by vertue of their power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, haue and do promiſe vnder obligation, of all and each their aforeſaide maſters goodes preſent and to come, that they ſhall accompliſh, and inuioably obſerue this preſent treatie, as alſo to cauſe them to ratifie the ſame &amp; to deliuer the one to the other authentique letters, both ſigned and ſealed, which in
<pb facs="tcp:7702:12"/>
preſent treatie ſhalbe from word to worde inſerted and that within a moneth of the day and date of theſe preents in regarde of the ſaid Lordes, moſt Chriſtian King, Cardinall of <hi>Auſtrie</hi> &amp; Duke of <hi>Sauoy:</hi> which Lord Archeduke hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed within thrée moneths to procure like letters of ratification of the ſame king Catholike. Moreouer the ſaide Deputies haue and doe promiſe by vertue and in the name aforeſaide (that kéepe the ſaid Letters of ratification of the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named moſt Chriſtian King, Cardinall, Archeduke and Duke of <hi>Sauoy)</hi> furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaide Chriſtian King Cardinall, Archeduke and Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> ſhall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſweare and take their othes vpon the Croſſe, holy Euangeliſts, Canon of the Maſſe, and vpon their honors, in preſence of ſuch as it ſhall pleaſe them to appoint: to obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue, accompliſh, whollie and reallie the tontents of the ſaid trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie: and like oathe ſhalbe done by the ſaid catholike King within thrée monethes after or when it ſhalbe required. In witneſſe whereof the ſaide Deputies haue ſubſcribed this preſent treatie with their names, in the place of <hi>Vreuin</hi> this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of May, <hi>anno.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>
               <hi>The Articles of the peace concluded vpon the Caſtel</hi> of Cambreſis, betwene the moſt high &amp; mighty Kings, PHILLIP <hi>by the grace of God, Catholike King of Spaine &amp;c. And the</hi> late HENRY the ſecond of that name moſt Chriſtian King of France.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Confirmation of the agreement made and concluded at <hi>Ryſſell</hi> and <hi>Cercamp.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis,</hi> that the aboue named Kings inuiolably obſerue theſe Treaties, &amp; aſſiſt one another in common counſaile.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Belonging to the reſtitution of the places of both ſides vnlawfully poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, that the King who firſt doth render them, chooſe out of the others coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try foure ſuch perſonages for pledges as he ſhall think good, vntill ſuch time as reſtitution of the other ſide be likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Don Charles</hi> ſonne to the King of Spaine ſhall haue in mariage the eldeſt daughter of the King of Fraunce, and for her dowrie ſhall haue foure hundreth thouſand Crownes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Emanuell</hi> Duke of Sauoy ſhall take in mariage the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> ſiſter vnto the King of Fraunce, and for her dowrie ſhall haue 300000. crownes, and render vnto the King his brother the Dukedome of <hi>Berry</hi> during his life.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:7702:13"/>4. All places citties &amp; freedomes, which the King detayneth ſhall be reſtord to the ſaide Duke, except, that the Kinge of <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſhall holde for the ſpace of fiue yeare, fiue citties in <hi>Piemont,</hi> viz. <hi>Turryn, Anguerry, Chinas, Quiers.</hi> and the newe cittie <hi>Daſt</hi> with the fortreſſes and iuriſdictictions of the ſame, within which time the king ſhal yéeld vp all his rights of the ſaid Cities.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Likewiſe ſhall the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hold two places and citties in <hi>Piemont</hi> viz. <hi>Vrſell</hi> and <hi>Aſte:</hi> the which he ſhal redeliuer with their iuriſdictions &amp; rights, when the king of <hi>France</hi> doth render his.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall render vnto the king of <hi>French S. Quintin. Han,</hi> and <hi>Chaſtelet,</hi> in ſuch ſort and eſtate as they are, except the artillarie and victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailes: where againſt, the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhall render <hi>Didenhouen,</hi> or <hi>Theon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille, Mommedy, Mais,</hi> and <hi>Marienborgh,</hi> with like conditions.</p>
            <p n="7">7 He alſo ſhall render vnto the Biſhop of <hi>Luic, Billo,</hi> with what elſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth belonging to the ſaid Lords.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Touching the cittie of <hi>Iuois,</hi> the king of <hi>France</hi> ſhall cauſe the walles and fortreſſes thereof to be pulled downe in recompence of <hi>Turrouane,</hi> and there ſhall be no more fortreſſes built there.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Terouan</hi> is rendred to the king of <hi>France,</hi> in all liberty as was before, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that no fortreſſes may be built vpon the ground.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The county of <hi>Mountferat</hi> returneth to the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> &amp; the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhalbe returned vnto him in the behalfe of both the kings, except the artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and victualles ſhalbe carried out, and if they think good, they may pul downe the fortraſſes which they haue made therein.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Thoſe of <hi>Charlois</hi> render themſelues againe vnder the king of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 The Baliage of <hi>Heſden</hi> with all rights and freedomes returne againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> without that the king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> haue any iuriſdiction therein with all fortreſſes.</p>
            <p n="13">13 The county of S. <hi>Poll</hi> ſhalbe held by the Lady of <hi>Tuteuile,</hi> the two kings notwithſtanding keepe their rights, the which laying aſide, king <hi>Phillip</hi> ſhall haue the ſouerannity thereof</p>
            <p n="14">14 The <hi>French</hi> ſhall hold <hi>Calis</hi> for eight yeares, and after giue the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and for pledges thereof ſhall the king of <hi>France</hi> ſet ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for a million of gold, and beſide ſend any of his Lords into <hi>England,</hi> whom they will chooſe, who ſhall remaine there vntill the reſtitution of the ſaid cittie of <hi>Calis</hi> and the king of <hi>France</hi> ſhall there with all quite renounce all the right which he might pretend thereto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7702:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
